DIRTY AND DISGUSTING
（又髒又噁心）
SHUT DOWN ALREADY!
（快倒閉吧！）
THEY SERVE BUG RAMEN
（他們的拉麵有蟲）
UNSANITARY DON'T GO HERE
（不衛生，別來這裡！）
DIRTY, GROSS, RIP-OFF
（骯髒，噁心，破舊）
RAMEN SETOYA
（瀨戶家拉麵）
I'm sorry. I'm really sorry.
對不起，真的很對不起
Sis.
姐
I'll drop out and work.
我會休學，然後去工作
What?
什麼？
I know we don't have any money.
我知道我們沒錢
I decided long ago.
我很久以前就決定了
Don't you want to study?
但你不想念書嗎？
I don't care about studying!
我才不在乎念書！
I'm an idiot anyway.
反正我是笨蛋
Here.
你拿著
Everyone has gotten much better in a short period. Well done.
大家在短時間內 都進步了很多，你們做得很好
Seto, you improved a lot.
瀨戶，你進步了很多
I'll deal with our debt somehow.
債務的事我會想辦法處理的
SAKURAGI
（櫻木）
I'm broke…
我要破產啦…
Why the stupid face?
怎麼擺出這種笨臉？
Whose fault do you think that is?
你覺得是誰的錯呢？
Who?
誰？
All of these are your receipts and invoices.
這些全都是老師你的收據和發票
I really might have to take out a loan.
我可能真的需要貸款了
Don't borrow from a sketchy place.
別找可疑的地方借錢
This is your problem too.
這也是你的問題
Oh, yeah.
對了
This one too.
還有這個
Give me a break!
給我適可而止吧！
Ramen Eiraku?
永樂拉麵？
You didn't go to Setoya.
你沒去瀨戶家
Setoya was closed.
瀨戶家關門了
You went?
你去了？
Sir?
老師？
What happened to Seto?
瀨戶怎麼了？
He's been away for three days. Isn't that strange?
他消失了三天 你們不覺得很奇怪嗎？
He leaves all my messages on read.
我傳的訊息他都已讀不回
He hasn't updated his YouTube since that day.
從那天開始 他就沒更新他的YouTube了
What's this?
這是什麼？
They borrowed from loan sharks.
他們和高利貸借錢
Oh, no. Sir, we have to help them.
怎麼會這樣？ 老師，我們一定要幫他們
No, loan sharks these days know how to stay hidden.
不，現在的高利貸都懂得隱身幕後
They use clever tactics.
他們懂得用聰明的技倆
-But we can't leave him… -Leave him.
-但我們不能這樣放任不管… -別管了
How coldhearted!
真是冷血！
Your job is to get our students into UTokyo.
妳的工作是將學生送進東大
This isn't about that. Seto is…
這和那無關，瀨戶他…
You asked me to come here.
是妳要我過來的
Do you remember? How did you convince me to come?
妳還記得嗎？ 妳是怎麼說服我過來的？
Answer in five words.
用8個字回答
Revitalize the school, make bank, Toranomon.
讓學校重生，賺錢回虎之門
That's six.
那是11個字
Good grief.
真是
Don't worry about Seto. Focus on your studies.
別擔心瀨戶了，專心念書吧
-Huh? -Isn't that coldhearted?
什麼？那不是很冷血嗎？
Hayase, what are the rules of the UTokyo Special Course?
早瀨，東大專科的規則是什麼？
Don't tell your parents.
不要讓父母知道
And?
還有呢？
Even if you can't understand the reason, do what the teacher says.
就算不明白原因 也要按老師說的去做
Then focus on your studies.
那就專心念書
Yes sir…
是
Listen, everyone. We're trying something new from today.
聽著，今天起我們會嘗試一些新東西
What is the most important thing to win a battle?
要贏一場比賽，最重要的是什麼？
Amano.
天野
Ambition.
野心
Um, yeah, that too.
嗯，那也是
Iwasaki.
岩崎
If it were me,
我的話
I'd research my opponent's weak points,
我會去研究對手的弱點
and attack them relentlessly, I guess?
然後往那裡不斷攻擊，應該是吧？
You're right!
答對了
To win a battle,
要贏一場比賽
you must understand the weak points.
你必須先瞭解弱點
Your own weak points.
你自己的弱點
Our own weak points?
我們自己的弱點？
Overcome your weak points through repetition.
透過重複來克服弱點
That's the shortcut to passing the exam.
這就是通過考試的捷徑
Oh is that it?
原來是這樣啊
Just studying hard is a waste of time.
僅僅用功念書是在浪費時間
All of you, your starting line
你們每位，你們的起跑線
is several hundred meters back.
是其他人的幾百米之後
But I don't know what I don't know… I mean…
但我不知道自己不懂哪些地方…
Yeah, there's so much I don't know!
嗯，我不知道的東西太多了
That's where this comes in.
這就是它登場的時候了
-Mizuno? -This.
-水野 -這個
A smartphone?
智慧型手機？
Study Sapuri.
學習補品
Study Sapuri looks at your study history,
學習補品會觀察你們的學習記錄
and what you understand and don't understand
而你們理解和不理解的部分
is made into data.
會被轉換成資料
You can visualize your strong and weak areas.
可以具體地看到自己的強項和弱點
You can see it at a glance, so you can study efficiently.
一目了然，你們就可以更高效地學習
Isn't that just for taking online classes?
但那不就是線上課程而已嗎？
Using an app to study seems lazy.
用手機來學習，感覺有點偷懶
That's nonsense!
那是胡說八道！
He who masters IT, masters the exam! That's common sense.
誰掌握了資訊技術 就掌握了考試！那是常識
Use Study Sapuri to root out your weaknesses.
首先，用學習補品 把你們的弱點連根拔起
Oh yeah, I almost forgot.
對了，我差點忘了
Today,
今天
Mizuno has a special present for you all.
水野有個特別禮物要送給你們
-Huh? -Bring them out.
-什麼？ -拿出來吧
Ma'am, you're so kind!
老師，妳真好！
Okay.
好
So, what's happening?
所以，怎麼樣了？
With the Elite University Course.
一流大學課程
Well…
是
Fujii has really taken the loss hard.
那次失敗狠狠打擊了藤井
He seems to be studying very hard.
看來他正很努力地念書
This honorific, "mogana" is an ending particle indicating desire.
這個敬語是表示意願的結尾詞
It indicates a wish for something. This also…
它代表了對某事的願望，這也…
Fujii is a jerk but he can study.
藤井是個混蛋，但他很擅長念書
But Chairman!
但是，理事長
The idea to stop the Top Uni Course and make the Elite University Course
停辦難關大課程，開辦一流大學課程
was brilliant!
真是個好主意！
As long as no more students join the UTokyo Course, it doesn't matter.
只要沒有更多學生 加入東大專科，這都不重要
Make sure Sakuragi doesn't do anything weird.
確保那個櫻木不會做什麼怪事
Keep an eye on him.
給我盯著他
Ugly and stupid can go to UTokyo!
笨蛋和醜女都給我上東大！
Yes, ma'am.
是
IDIOT
（笨蛋）
I-Idiot?
笨…笨蛋？
This is our present?
這是我們的禮物？
Yes.
沒錯
Whenever there are problems you can't solve,
每當你們有解不開的問題時
we'll have you study with these "idiot" headbands.
我們會讓你們 戴著這些“笨蛋”頭巾學習
-Huh? -We'll wear this?!
-什麼？ -我們要戴著個？
It is a headband after all.
畢竟這是個頭巾
If you solve the problem, you can take it off.
要是解開了問題，你們就能拿下它
And if you find another you can't solve,
要是你們又找到解不開的另一題
you put on the headband.
你們就得再戴上頭巾
Once you learn it, take it off. And if you keep repeating that,
學會了就脫下，如果你們不斷重複
you will have no problems you can't solve.
就不會有解不開的問題了
It's not that simple.
才沒有那麼簡單
I did this very thing and got into UTokyo.
我也做了一樣的事，最終考上了東大
Really?
真的？
It's embarrassing, isn't it?
因為這個很丟臉啊，是吧？
Of course it is.
當然了
I also think this is too…
我也這麼覺得…
That's why it works. When it comes to motivation for effort,
這就是為什麼它有用，說到動力
negative emotions have more power than positive emotions.
負面情緒比正面情緒更有力
You don't want to look silly,
你不想看起來很笨
so you work hard at the problems.
所以你會努力解開問題
When you solve them, you can remove the headband.
當你理解了問題，你也可以解開頭巾
That eventually becomes pleasurable, and before you know it,
你會漸漸享受這過程，在你發現之前
you have a positive attitude towards studying.
你對學習就有了一種正向的態度
That may be theoretically true, but…
理論上可能是對的，但…
Kaede?
楓？
Fine.
好吧
Huh? Then, me too.
咦？好吧，我也…
Okay! I'll put it on you.
來，我幫你戴
Wow! It looks good.
哇！真適合你
Ready?
準備好了嗎？
Idiots!
笨蛋！
They're acting weird at the UTokyo Special Course.
東大專科又做怪事了
Really? What's that?
真的？他們在幹嘛？
No way, that's crazy!
不可能，真是瘋了！
Hey, look! They're really doing it!
你看，他們真的戴著耶
Are they that serious about getting into UTokyo? So cringe!
他們是認真要進東大？也太扯了吧
"Hinemosu."
“終日”
I'm embarrassed!
好丟臉！
"Hinemosu" is a strange word.
“終日”的念法真奇怪
"So as to" means "in order to."
“So as to” 意思是“為了”
"So as to," "in order to."
“So as to”，“為了”
They're looking at us…
他們在看我們…
In reflection transformations, plus and minus are reversed.
反射變換中，正負會顛倒
You're welcome anytime.
隨時歡迎你們
Go to UTokyo and your life will change dramatically!
上東大，徹底顛覆你的人生！
Hey, Fujii.
藤井
-Did you come to see? -Shut up.
-你來看我們嗎？ -閉嘴
Watch as much as you like.
你想看多少就看吧
A job?
打工？
I'll do anything. Could you hire me?
我什麼都做，你能請我嗎？
-No way. -Why?
-不行 -為什麼？
You're a Tatsumi student.
你是龍海的學生
They're banned from working. If I hired you, it'd be my neck.
他們禁止打工，要是請你我就完了
These "idiot" headbands really are embarrassing.
那些“笨蛋”頭巾也太丟人了
That's for sure.
是啊
How about you? Aren't you embarrassed?
楓，妳呢？妳不覺得丟臉嗎？
If it means my grades go up, I don't mind.
要是這樣我成績能變好，我不在乎
Nobody's looking anyway.
反正沒人看
Everyone was looking! You were really concentrating…
大家都在看！妳的專注力也太強了
Hey, you wanna go?
嘿，妳要去嗎？
-Huh? -Go? Go where?
-什麼？ -去哪裡？
Don't think about it, just do it!
別想太多，做就對了！
Everyone's really gotten into the groove.
大家越來越跟得上節奏了
You're still so naive.
妳還是那麼單純啊
Yeah, yeah.
是啦
I'm hungry.
我餓了
I want some gyoza.
我想吃餃子
This is a bad idea.
這不太好吧？
Huh? What's wrong with it?
啊？有什麼問題？
Our teacher told us to forget about Seto.
老師叫我們忘了瀨戶
You really are heartless. I bet you don't have any friends.
你真是無情，我猜你一定沒朋友吧
I don't! I don't, but…
才不是！我是沒有…
What're you doing in front of my house?
你們在我家門前幹嘛？
Seto!
瀨戶！
Long time no see.
好久不見
-Yeah. -We came to have some ramen.
-嗯 -我們過來吃拉麵
Thanks! That was delicious!
謝謝招待，真美味！
What are you doing?
妳在幹嘛？
I'm posting it on my hip schoolgirl Twitter account.
我要把這上傳到我的推特帳號
You're keeping it up!
妳還有繼續用啊
Of course I am! Thanks to this, we beat Fujii after all.
當然了！多虧這個，我們打敗了藤井
Yeah. It could be thanks to my YouTube too.
也是，也多虧了我的YouTube
Yeah it was!
是啊
You had your ramen, now get out of here.
你們吃完拉麵趕緊走吧
How rude!
什麼啊？
We came because we're worried about you!
我們來這是因為擔心你！
Look, I even promoted your restaurant.
你看，我還幫你的拉麵店宣傳
Nobody asked you to worry about me.
沒人叫你們擔心我
You only have 13 followers, so how does that help anyway?
妳的粉絲只有13個，能幫到什麼？
Go on, go home.
快點回去啦
Worrying was a waste of time! Let's go!
擔心你真是浪費時間，走吧
Thanks for the food!
多謝款待
You're coming back to class, right?
你會回來專科，對吧？
Once things settle down.
等事情都平復之後吧
Welcome!
歡迎！
We've got customers, so go.
我們有客人了，妳走吧
Thanks for the food.
謝謝款待
Kaede, what is it?
楓，怎麼了？
-Nothing. -Ah.
-沒事 -啊
Ah!
啊！
-Oh no! Let's go! -Yeah.
-糟了！走吧！ -嗯
-Kaede! Hurry! -It's bad!
-楓！快點！ -出事了！
What? Hey, what is it?
什麼？等一下，發生了什麼事？
-It's Mr. Sakuragi! -What? Oh no!
-櫻木老師他們來了！ -什麼？糟糕！
-Pardon me. -Yes?
-不好意思 -是
-This was in my food. -Mine had this.
-這在我的食物裡 -我的是這個
I almost ate it!
我差點吃進去了！
I'm sorry.
不好意思
But that's not ours.
但我們店裡沒有這些東西
-Even so, it was in there. -You talk to customers like that?
-即便如此，它在碗裡啊 -你是這樣和顧客說話嗎？
This place has a bad attitude!
這地方的態度真差！
There's no way that was in there!
我們的麵裡才不會有這些東西！
I'm very sorry!
實在很對不起！
-You don't have to apologize to them! -Akira!
-妳不用和這種傢伙道歉！ -輝！
Hey, hey! That's terrible customer service.
喂！真是糟糕的服務！
Everyone!
大家！
Watch out!
小心點！
This place puts stuff in the food!
這家店會在食物裡放東西！
There!
你看！
Forcible obstruction of business.
強行妨害業務罪
Shouting false information in a restaurant.
在餐廳裡散播假消息
Causing a fuss.
造成混亂
-Right? -Huh?
-對吧？ -什麼？
Ah, yes, article 234 of the penal code.
啊，是刑法第234條
Who are you two?
你們兩個是誰？
Hey. Let's go.
喂，走吧
One more thing. Those papers that were put up.
還有一件事，那些張貼在外面的紙張
That was you guys, right?
是你們幹的，對吧？
That's fraudulent obstruction of business.
那是損毀信用和妨害業務
Article 233 of the penal code.
這是刑法第233條
So you admit it.
所以你承認了
-Let's go. -Yeah.
-走吧 -嗯
-Hey! -Leave it.
-喂！ -別管了
It doesn't matter what you say.
跟那些人說什麼都沒用
They're just hired by the loan sharks.
他們只是拿高利貸的錢辦事
Yes, sir.
是
This is terrible.
真是糟糕
Why are you here?
你怎麼在這裡？
I came to eat ramen at a ramen restaurant!
我來拉麵店吃拉麵，有什麼問題？
Sis?!
姐
Are you okay?
妳還好嗎？
I'm just a little tired.
我只是有點累
Go rest in the back.
去後面休息吧
This is so good.
真好吃
You've got good skills.
你真有兩下子
At a time like this?
都什麼時候了
Seto, are you okay?
瀨戶，你還好嗎？
I've worked at my family's restaurant so I know what it's like.
我也在家裡的餐廳工作過 所以我能明白
You can talk to us.
你可以和我們聊聊
When our parents died three years ago, they had debt.
三年前去世的父母，留下了一筆債
My sister worked hard to pay it off,
我姐姐為了還清債務，很努力工作
but she couldn't meet the deadlines.
但她沒辦法趕上還款期限
Half a year ago, she found a finance company that would lend us money.
半年前，她找到了一家 願意借我們錢的信貸公司
She was going to pay it right back.
她當時打算很快就還款
But that million yen debt just kept growing,
但一百萬圓的債務不斷變多
and now we can't keep up at all.
等我們留意到時，已經跟不上了
-So what will you do? -That's why…
-那你打算怎麼做？ -所以…
I'm looking for a job. All I can do is work.
我正在找工作，我現在就只能工作
Our school bans students from working.
我們學校禁止學生打工
If I don't work, my family is finished!
要是我不工作，我家就完了！
Idiot. You could never earn enough to make a dent in that debt.
笨蛋，你無論掙多少 都不夠償還那筆債的
This is my problem. I don't want to bother anyone else.
這是我的問題，我不想麻煩其他人
You're up against a loan shark!
你對抗的可是高利貸
We're lawyers.
我們是律師
We can help you.
我們可以幫助你
I told you. I don't want to bother anyone!
我剛說了，我不想麻煩其他人！
So you're giving up on UTokyo?
那你要放棄東大了嗎？
I could never get into UTokyo anyway.
反正我本來就不可能進東大
Okay, I got it.
這樣啊，我明白了
Sir!
老師！
Don't tell the others.
別跟專科的其他人說
Don't interrupt their studies.
別影響他們念書
Please.
拜託了
Thanks for the food.
謝謝款待
Wait, sir!
等一下，老師！
Sir! Wait!
老師，請等一下
What is it?
幹嘛？
Why won't you help Seto?
你為什麼不幫瀨戶？
I can't if he feels that way.
他這麼想的話，我也沒辦法
But we're lawyers.
但我們是律師
Loan sharks are professional criminals.
高利貸是專業罪犯
Play on their field,
去侵犯他們的地盤
and Tatsumi Gakuen will be affected next.
龍海學園也會遭殃
This badge means at any time, under any circumstances,
這徽章代表著任何時候，任何情況
we aim for freedom and justice, fairness and equality.
我們都追求自由、正義、公正和平等
Ignoring this goes against what a lawyer should do.
忽視這件事，違反了律師的操守
Harassing people at work is their modus operandi.
在工作場合騷擾他人 是他們的慣用手法
The chairman would be chased out. The Special Course, too.
理事長會被趕出去，專科也一樣
And your ambitions!
還有妳的志願！
That's not what Seto wants.
這不是瀨戶想要的
But we can't just do nothing…
但我們不能什麼都不做…
Stop worrying about Seto and think about them!
別擔心瀨戶了，想想其他人吧！
I've got an early day tomorrow.
明天我要早起
I'm going home to sleep. Don't call me.
我回家睡覺了，別打電話給我
Hang on, wait!
等一下！
Math is so hard!
數學好難啊！
NAO I SEARCHED SETO'S…
（菜緒：我在網路上搜了瀨戶家…）
I searched Seto's ramen place online.
我在網路上搜了瀨戶家拉麵
There are some really bad reviews.
上面有些非常過分的評論
Huh?
什麼？
RAMEN SETOYA
（瀨戶家）
This place serves ramen with bugs in it.
這地方的拉麵有蟲
Setoya is the worst in Japan.
瀨戶家真是全日本最差
This place is terrible!
這地方糟透了！
Their service is so bad, even if you go…
他們的服務態度太差了 就算你去了…
NAO MAYBE SOMEONE HAS…
（蔡緒）
Maybe someone has a grudge?
是不是招惹了仇家啊？
Nao, I'm coming in.
菜緒，我進來啦
Don't just barge in like that.
別就這樣走進來啊
Lately, whenever you're home,
最近，妳一回家
you always just hide in your room.
就老是躲在房間裡
I'm just studying.
我只是在念書
"Idiot"?
“笨蛋”？
It's nothing!
那沒什麼啦！
Forget about it, just go!
別管了，妳出去吧！
-Nao… -Okay, okay.
-菜緒… -好啦
Hey bro, how's the UTokyo Special Course going?
哥哥，東大專科進行得怎麼樣了？
You could knock.
你可以敲門
Hang on, how do you know about that?
等一下，你怎麼知道的？
My old buddy goes to Tatsumi, and he told me.
我朋友在龍海，他跟我說的
Promise you won't tell mom.
答應我，別跟媽媽說
Why?
為什麼？
It's a UTokyo Special Course rule.
這是東大專科的規則
So heavy.
好重啊
Iwasaki, what is it?
岩崎，怎麼了？
Oh, nothing.
不，沒什麼
Kaede is worried about Seto.
楓很擔心瀨戶
What? You guys should forget about Seto.
我怎麼說的？你們應該忘了瀨戶的事
And focus on studying. As I told you.
專心念書，我跟你們說過了
I know that.
我知道
But I have a bad feeling.
但我有不好的預感
Is he really okay?
他真的沒事嗎？
Well…
這個嘛…
Pardon me. Mr. Sakuragi!
不好意思，櫻木老師！
We have trouble!
我們有麻煩了！
What?
什麼？
-You going to class? -Nope.
-你要上課嗎？ -誰要上啊？
-This is good! -Yeah, it's good!
-這個不錯耶 -對啊，不錯
They came to the school? But why?
她們來學校了？為什麼？
They want to talk to the UTokyo Special Course teachers.
她們要見東大專科的老師
Anyway, they seemed very angry. Hurry!
總之她們看起來很生氣，快點！
Pardon me.
不好意思
"These guys are trying for UTokyo," it says.
上面寫著：“這些人想上東大”
How much of a jerk can Fujii be?
藤井這傢伙是能有多混蛋？
Whoa, it's got so many retweets.
哇，好多人轉推
It really does…
真的耶…
If she sees this, my mom will freak out.
我媽要是看到這個一定會抓狂
My mom would be against it too, I know it.
我媽也肯定會反對
What should we do?
我們該怎麼辦？
Why is my child trying out for UTokyo?
我孩子怎麼會想上東大？
Is there a problem?
這有什麼問題？
My Nao could never get into UTokyo!
我家菜緒不可能考上東大！
Could never get in?
不可能考上？
Well, what do you think, Mrs. Amano?
那麼天野太太，妳又是怎麼想的呢？
He did poorly on his junior high exam and got into Tatsumi Gakuen.
他國中考試成績很差，進了龍海學園
I don't want it to happen again in high school!
我不希望這種事情在高中再發生！
Are you saying Koichiro will do poorly?
妳的意思是晃一郎會考得很差？
Yes, he will! It's UTokyo!
當然啊，那可是東大！
Are you toying with our children?
你是在玩弄我們的孩子嗎？
-That's not our intention… -Then what's this?
-我們沒有這個意圖… -那這是什麼？
You made them wear this!
你們讓他們戴上這個！
If you're not toying with them, then what?
這不是玩弄他們是什麼？
I demand an explanation!
我要求解釋！
I see.
我明白了
Then shall we include the students in this discussion?
那我們是否該讓學生們一起來討論？
I'm not sure the children should hear…
櫻木老師 我不確定孩子們是否應該聽…
It's their lives we're talking about.
我們討論的可是他們的人生
They have a right to hear.
他們有聽的權利
Hayase and Amano's mothers have come to the Special Course.
東大專科的早瀨和天野的母親來了
The excitement never stops, does it?
有趣的事真是一件接一件，對吧？
They might demand they leave the Special Course.
她們可能會要求孩子們退出東大專科
I would appreciate it if they did.
如果她們這麼要求，我會很感激
Pardon me.
失陪了
That was dangerous!
好危險！
Don't run in the halls! Don't run!
別在走廊上跑，別跑啊！
Is that…?
那是…
You said I was toying with Nao and Koichiro.
妳們說我玩弄菜緒和晃一郎
But I have no intention of that.
但我沒這個意思
I'm serious.
我是認真的
-But… -Here's why.
-但… -要說為什麼的話
When we started the Special Course,
我們剛要開辦東大專科時
I mocked all of the students.
我嘲笑了全校所有學生
But out of all of them, only Nao and Koichiro
但他們所有人中，只有菜緒和晃一郎
came and said "We want to go to UTokyo."
來到我這裡說：“我們想去東大”
Just two out of 645 students.
645位學生中只有兩位
Don't you think that's amazing?
不覺得很了不起嗎？
My Nao?
我家菜緒嗎？
People who accomplish great things are all like this.
所有能成大事的人都是這樣的
No matter how steep the road,
無論路多麼顛簸
they have the strong will to push forward.
他們都有往前推的意志力
Those two have that.
這兩位有著那個意志力
They already have what they need most to pass the UTokyo entrance exam.
他們已經具備了 通過東大入學考最重要的東西
But why did they keep it from us?
那他們為什麼瞞著我們呢？
I told them to.
我叫他們這麼做的
Huh?
什麼？
And the thing you just said is the reason why.
妳們剛剛說的話就是這麼做的原因
"She could never get in."
“她不可能考上的”
"He'll do poorly again."
“他又會考得很差”
I'm saying, parents don't trust their children.
也就是家長不信任自己的孩子
How rude! I trust Koichiro very much.
真是失禮，我非常信任晃一郎！
So why do you think failing is a foregone conclusion?
那妳為什麼覺得失敗是必然的結果？
Are you trying to stop him from trying?
妳是不是想阻止他嘗試？
That's…
那是…
The way to crush a child's strong will
粉碎孩子堅強意志力的
is a parent's rejection.
是家長的否定
I'm not rejecting anything.
我沒在否定什麼
When a teen consults with their parents,
青少年問父母意見時
the result is nearly always a rejection.
結果通常都是拒絕
You two just said,
妳們兩位剛剛說
"My child could never get into UTokyo."
“我的孩子不可能考上東大”
Didn't you?
對吧？
But it's UTokyo after all.
但怎麼說都是東大啊
Okay, one question.
好，我有一個問題
Many people come to Japan from Taiwan for sightseeing.
很多台灣人到日本觀光
What areas of Japan would be popular tourist destinations?
日本的哪些區域 會成為他們的熱門景點？
Other than Kyoto and Nara, answer with some locations.
除了京都和奈良，請回答一些地點
-What is this, suddenly? -A quiz at a time like this?
-這是什麼？那麼突然？ -這種時候出常識問答？
I would say Chiba.
我覺得是千葉
What's the reason?
理由是什麼？
That's where Disneyland is.
因為迪士尼樂園在那裡
We have USJ too, so Osaka is also probably good.
我們還有環球影城 所以大阪應該也會受歡迎
You're right.
答對了
Amano?
天野呢？
I think it's Hokkaido.
我想是北海道
Your reason?
你的原因是？
Snow doesn't fall in Taiwan, so leisure spots with snow
我聽說台灣不下雪 所以有雪的觀光地區
are popular, I heard.
應該會有人氣
That's correct too.
這也正確
Like I said, a quiz? We're here to talk to you.
搞什麼常識問答？ 我們是來找你討論的
-This isn't a quiz. -Huh?
-這不是常識問答 -什麼？
That was a geography question on the 2010 UTokyo entrance exam.
那是2010年東大入學考的地理題
-A UTokyo question? -That?
-東大的題目？ -就那個？
-I knew it. -I thought so.
-我就知道 -我也想到了
And both of them got it right. The reasoning just needs to be clear.
沒錯，而他們兩位都答對了 理由清楚就夠了
Yay!
好耶！
It was like the question on our test the other day.
這和那天測試的問題一樣
Your test the other day?
那天的測試？
These two studied for just three weeks,
這兩位只學了三個星期
battled the top student in their year, and won.
和他們同年級的優等生比賽，還贏了
Is that true?
真的嗎？
My Koichiro?
晃一郎嗎？
The biggest enemy of an entrance exam is the preconceived idea that you'll fail.
入學考最大的敵人 是先入為主，覺得會肯定失敗的想法
That rigid way of thinking.
那種固化的思考模式
And who are the ones worst at instilling that mindset?
最常灌輸這心態的人是誰呢？
Parents.
家長
Can you trust your own children?
妳能相信妳的孩子嗎？
How rude. I always trust Nao.
真無禮，我一直都相信菜緒
My second son, a first-year high schooler, is aiming for UTokyo.
我讀高一的二兒子目標是考上東大
Plus I think Koichiro has higher abilities than those other kids.
我也認為晃一郎 比其他孩子們能力更強
"Those other kids"?
“其他孩子們”？
For the two of you, I have something I want you to follow.
那麼我有些事要請妳們照著做
Mizuno.
水野
"Ten Family Rules for Getting into UTokyo."
“東大合格必勝法，十大家庭條規”
That sounds impressive.
聽起來好厲害
You three read it for us.
你們三位念給我們聽
1. Eat breakfast together.
一，一起吃早餐
2. Have them do some housework.
二，讓他們做一些家事
3. Make them get some exercise.
三，讓他們做適度的運動
4. Have them take a bath at the same time every day.
四，確保他們每天在同一時間洗澡
5. Let them rest when they're not well.
五，不舒服的時候，讓他們休息
6. Keep the living room tidy.
六，確保客廳整潔
7. Don't hassle them about studying.
七，不要因為念書的事煩擾他們
8. Get along as husband and wife.
八，夫妻和睦共處
9. Eat out once a month as a family.
九，全家每月出去用餐一次
10. Share these rules with the father.
十，與孩子的父親分享這些規則
It's nothing special.
沒什麼特別的
The normal lifestyle of a normal family.
普通家庭的平凡生活方式
Just do that.
這麼做就對了
By obeying these ten rules for a year,
但透過遵循這十條規則一年
your children can definitely get into UTokyo.
妳們的孩子絕對可以考上東大
Rule two, about housework.
第二條，關於家事
My child is a boy.
我孩子是個男的
Housework isn't for boys or girls.
家事不是男孩或女孩的事
Have him do what he can.
他能做什麼就讓他做什麼
Clean the foyer every morning, or the tub every evening.
每早清理玄關，或晚上清理浴缸
Anyhow, there's a lot he can do.
無論如何，有很多是他可以做的
The important thing about entrance exams is preserving your daily life.
入學考很重要的是保持日常生活
Daily life?
日常生活？
Entrance exams make people want to study all the time.
入學考讓人想要沒日沒夜地念書
The family gets disrupted.
全家生活也會被打亂
Children are sensitive.
孩子們很敏感
They feel bad for burdening their family.
對家庭造成負擔，他們會覺得愧疚
And that becomes pressure.
那會變成壓力
They could even abandon the exam.
他們甚至會因此放棄考試
In order to avoid that sort of mistake, the family's daily life
為了避免這種情況，家庭的日常生活
should not be changed.
不能被打亂
It seems difficult.
聽起來很難
For example, if you go on holiday every summer,
比如說，如果妳每個夏天都去度假
you should still go, even for a short time.
妳還是該繼續去，即使只去一下子
-Really? It's okay? -It's fine! Go on!
-真的嗎？這樣可以嗎？ -那沒問題，去吧
We don't really take holidays.
我們不太去度假
You can eat breakfast together.
你們可以一起吃早餐
Take a bath at the same time every day. That's plenty.
每天在同一時間洗澡，還有很多
A regular lifestyle develops good habits.
規律的生活方式能養成良好的習慣
And the study cycle is created.
那就形成了念書週期
Studying will become natural.
念書變得很自然
Victory is certain.
勝利就成為必然
Students who value daily life,
重視日常生活的學生
will beat the exam.
會贏得考試
By the way, rule eight.
話說，第八條
Get along as husband and wife.
夫妻和睦共處
The foundation of a peaceful daily life is harmony between husband and wife.
換句話說 平靜日常的基礎是夫妻和諧
That's one thing we can't control.
那是我們不能控制的
So I leave it to you.
所以我就拜託妳們了
If you have questions about anything else, come anytime.
要是妳們有任何問題，歡迎隨時過來
Okay.
好
Is that acceptable? Then if you don't mind, class is starting,
都沒問題嗎？ 如果妳們不介意，我們要開始上課了
so please be on your way.
麻煩妳們先離開了
-Hey, new hire! -Yes, sir.
-喂，新來的！ -是
There's a customer. Stop spacing out.
客人來了，別再發呆了
-Do it right! -I'm sorry.
-給我把工作做好！ -不好意思
Welcome! Fill up the tank?
你好，油箱要加滿嗎？
A special math instructor, Tetsunosuke Yanagi.
數學特別講師，柳鐵之介老師
Sorry to keep you waiting. We had a sudden interruption.
不好意思讓您久等 剛剛臨時有事被打斷了
Always working the elderly so hard.
總是讓老人家那麼勞累
Mr. Yanagi, long time no see.
柳老師，好久不見
-Is that you, Mizuno? -Yes, sir.
-是妳嗎，水野？ -是的
He's like a wizard.
他真像個仙人
He looks frail…
他看起來顫顫巍巍的…
What?
什麼？
He's scary.
好可怕
So intimidating.
真有壓迫感
I have a bad feeling about this…
我有種不祥的預感…
Let's begin.
開始吧
You did your Study Sapuri,
你們做了學習補品
and you were all very weak in math.
結果是你們全部的數學都很弱
The basics are very important in math.
數學的基礎很重要
You've got to solidify your basics early.
你們需要早點打下基礎
-Amano, what do you think we should do? -Huh?
-天野，你覺得我們該做什麼？ -咦？
Go back to what we don't know and review?
回到我們不瞭解的部分重新複習？
Go back to when?
回到什麼時候？
High school first year?
高一？
No. Hayase.
不，早瀨
Junior high third year?
應該是國三吧？
-Iwasaki. -It's not that?
-岩崎 -不是那個？
Not… junior high first year?
該不會是…國一？
No. Mizuno.
不，水野
Elementary fifth grade.
小學五年級
You're going back
你們會回到
to elementary second grade.
小學二年級
-Second grade? -Yes.
-小學二年級？ -對
You're re-learning math from second grade.
你們會從小學二年起重新學
That's taking the idiot thing too far.
這也把我們看得太笨了
We're not that stupid.
我們沒有那麼笨
The reason why you can't do math
你們不會數學的原因
is because your calculation abilities are lacking.
是因為缺乏計算技巧
And the turning point for that is in the second grade.
而這的轉捩點是在二年級
If you're good at elementary second grade math,
要是你擅長小學二年級數學
you'll be able to study.
你就有學習的能力
What should we do?
我們該怎麼做？
This is why I invited the legendary math instructor Mr. Yanagi here.
這就是我把傳奇數學講師 柳老師請過來的原因
This old grandpa?
這個老爺爺？
Nice to meet you.
請多多指教
My teaching methods are Spartan.
我用的是斯巴達教學法
I don't care about the changing times or different study methods.
我不在乎時代改變，或是其它學習法
I'm going to cram it into you!
我會塞滿你們！
Cramming is true education.
塞滿知識才是真正的教育！
This is the Spartan you wanted. Be grateful.
如何？這就是 你們需要的斯巴達教學，感恩吧
Didn't you say this was behind the times, Mr. Sakuragi?
你不是說過這很過時嗎，櫻木老師？
To get your math up to speed, you need a period of Spartan study.
要快速進步數學 需要一段時間的斯巴達訓練
Training thoroughly is the most effective way.
徹底訓練是最有效的方法
Mr. Yanagi drilled it into me too.
我也被柳老師操練過
I got it.
我明白了
Let's do it.
我們做吧
Kaede…
楓…
No fair.
不公平！
Let's begin. Mizuno, hand those out.
開始吧，水野，把那些發給大家
I made these myself. A hundred practice questions.
這是我自己出的一百道練習題
I'll accept no less than 100%.
我只接受滿分的成績
What?!
什麼？
But this is easy.
但這很簡單
Oh, it is.
哦，真的耶
Let's begin.
開始
You have three minutes.
作答時間三分鐘
Three minutes?!
三分鐘？
Ready, start!
準備，開始！
The questions are second-grade level, but 100 in three minutes is tough.
這些問題都是小二程度 但三分鐘內答一百題還是很困難
And to get them all right…
而且要全答對…
98-14=84, 62-29=33…
98減去14等於84 62減去29等於33…
Ugh, I still have over half left.
我還剩一半以上的題
81-9=72, 1008-14=984…
81減去9等於72 1008減去14等於984…
I made a mistake.
啊，我做錯了一題
3x7=21, 2x6=12…
3乘以7等於21 2乘以6等於12…
Man, I have so many left!
天啊，我還有那麼多題！
Stop!
停！
I didn't finish in time.
根本沒辦法在時間內完成
It's no good…
不妙…
I don't even need to say this,
我都不必說出來
but you're far from 100%.
你們離滿分差遠了
But you're not especially inferior.
但你們並不比別人差
-Huh? -However.
-什麼？ -不過
You must focus or you won't acquire a tacit knowledge of numbers.
你們一定要專注 否則無法掌握數字的內隱知識
Tacit knowledge? What's that?
內隱知識？那是什麼？
The power to do it by feeling, without thinking.
不必思考，用感覺去做的能力
I don't really get it.
我不太明白
Do you think about riding a bike every time you do it?
你們騎腳踏車時會想怎麼做嗎？
You don't.
不會
You need to be able to do math without thinking about it.
做數學題時 你們得能不假思索地去做
That's tacit knowledge of numbers.
那就是數字的內隱知識
If you work on these elementary level problems,
如果你們在這些小學題目上努力
by summer you'll reach high school level.
到了夏天，你們就會達到高中程度
Okay, let's push through!
好，來加油吧！
No, you'll power through!
不止，你們要猛踩油門！
Here, dum-dum.
來，小笨
Ready, start!
準備，開始！
Stop!
停！
Start!
開始！
Take care.
保重
I can't… I'm dying.
不行…我要死了
I'm tired.
我好累
I'm done…
我不行了
That's what I like to see.
這就是我想看到的
That makes me so mad.
真讓人生氣
It's good. Studying is anger.
很好，學習就是憤怒
Get mad at yourself.
對自己做不到而憤怒吧
I'm starving.
我好餓
Yeah, I want to eat ramen at Setoya.
嗯，真想到瀨戶家吃拉麵
Sir, is Seto going to be okay?
老師，瀨戶真的沒事嗎？
Seto is fine.
瀨戶沒事
-You all focus on studying. -But I can't help…
-你們只管專心念書 -但我會忍不住…
Why can't you believe in Seto?
妳為什麼就不能相信瀨戶呢？
He's stubborn.
他很固執
He just takes a little longer than you.
他只是比你們慢一點
But right now,
但現在
he's doing what he can, using his own abilities.
他在用自己的力量盡力解決問題
-He's taking responsibility. -But sir…
-這是他自己的責任 -但是老師…
I got it.
我明白了
Kaede?
楓？
I'll focus on studying.
我會專心學習
It's our lives after all.
怎麼說，這都是我們的人生
I don't want to give up again.
我不想再放棄了
Alright, I'll do it one more time.
好，我會再做一次
Okay, let's do it.
好，做吧
Let's power through.
一起猛踩油門吧！
-Ma'am -Okay.
-老師 -好
Ready, start.
準備，開始
Sir?
老師？
I'm going out for some cigarettes.
我出去買菸
-Hey new hire. -Yes, sir?
-喂，新來的 -是
-The manager wants you. -Right away, sir.
-店長想見你 -好，馬上來
Hey, Akira!
喔，輝！
-Long time no see. -Hey.
-好久不見 -嗯
What are you guys doing?
你們在幹嘛？
You joined the UTokyo Special Course. Right?
你加入了東大專科，對吧？
We figured we should try studying.
我們覺得我們也該來念書
We probably can't get into UTokyo.
我們可能進不了東大
But Keio or Waseda should be a cinch!
但慶應或是早稻田應該是小問題！
Mr. Sakuragi said it.
櫻木老師說了
If you don't want adults to take advantage and exploit you, study!
如果你不想被成人世界 佔便宜、剝削，就念書吧！
Yeah, we're a little too shy to join the Special Course though.
但是嘛，要參加專科 我們還是不太好意思
Hello?
喂？
Huh?
什麼？
Why?!
為什麼？
Why are you here?
你為什麼在這裡？
Don't make me say it again.
別讓我再重複了
I came to eat ramen at a ramen restaurant.
我來拉麵店吃拉麵
Why so glum?
怎麼死氣沉沉的？
You get fired from your job?
你打工被開除了嗎？
How did you know?
你怎麼知道？
I happened to see you working at the gas station.
我剛好看到你在加油站打工
It was you! You ratted.
果然是你通風報信！
I am employed by Tatsumi Gakuen.
我受雇於龍海學園
I can't accept work that is banned by the school.
學校禁止的打工，我不能接受
-That's bullshit! -I've got something better.
-胡說八道！ -我有更好的提議
I've got a good offer for you.
我有個好機會給你
I'll tell you about a job that pays 4000 yen per hour.
我會告訴你一份時薪四千圓的工作
Four thousand per hour? There's no such thing.
一小時四千圓？那種工作不存在
There is. You go back to the Special Course and study.
存在的，你回去東大專科念書就有了
What are you saying?
你在說什麼？
UTokyo graduates earn about 500,000,000 yen in their lifetimes.
東大畢業生一輩子的收入 大約是五億圓
If you calculate that into one year of study,
如果你把一年的學習時間算進去
it's like a job that pays 4000 yen per hour.
那就像一份時薪四千圓的工作
I don't want to hear what-ifs.
我不想聽這種詭辯
Then, you're not coming back to the Special Course?
那你不回來東大專科了嗎？
You don't want to study?
你不想念書嗎？
You don't make me say it again!
你別讓我再重複！
If I don't work, we can't repay our debt!
如果我不去打工 就無法還我們的債！
Seto, you lost both your parents, and you grew up poor.
瀨戶，你失去了父母，在貧窮中長大
Everyone will sympathize with you.
大家都會同情你
But Seto.
但是瀨戶
If you want to change,
如果你想要改變
you have to use your head, and don't accept the status quo!
你得動腦筋，你不能接受現狀！
Listen, Seto. If you pass the entrance exam,
聽好了，瀨戶，要是你通過了入學考
even if you're poor, even if you have no parents,
即使你貧窮，即使你沒有父母
you can go to a top university.
你依然可以進入一流大學
You don't want to bother others?
你不想麻煩其他人？
That shitty pride isn't worth one yen.
那該死的自尊一文不值
Even a dumb kid nearly swallowed up by society's darkness,
即使是差點被社會的陰暗 所吞噬的笨小孩
if they pass the exam, can go to a top university.
要是通過考試，他也能進入一流大學
You can fix your life!
你可以重建你的人生！
But the debt!
但是債務！
I can't bother anyone!
我不能牽涉其他人！
If we can't pay them, they'll go to the school! If that happens--
要是不能付清，他們會就到學校去 要是這種事情發生…
-It's okay! -Huh?
-那沒關係了！ -什麼？
Look…
你看…
PAID IN FULL
（付清證明）
ONE MILLION YEN
（一百萬圓）
What's this…
這是什麼…
How?
怎麼會？
Mr. Sakuragi…
櫻木老師…
He got it all back.
他都討回來了
Huh?
什麼？
The loan shark you borrowed from was a little too forceful.
你們借的那個高利貸有點太強勢了
I looked into it, and I was right.
我調查了一下，發現我是對的
There were piles of evidence of their illegal activity.
他們的非法活動證據多得成堆
I used that to threaten to stop their business.
我用那來威脅他們停止營業
And it was an easy negotiation.
這是個輕鬆的談判
Negotiation?
談判？
Loan sharks these days use clever tricks to avoid being caught.
現在的高利貸 用高明的技倆來避免落網
But you can't get away with crime if you're stupid.
笨蛋還做不了壞事呢
You're scarier than a loan shark.
你比高利貸還要可怕
Don't be ridiculous. I'm a kind lawyer.
別亂說了，我是個善良的律師
Your sister's loan from the loan sharks,
這樣一來 你姐姐從高利貸借來的債務
your debt of one million yen is paid.
一百萬圓的債務已經還清了
The loan shark your sister used
你姐姐借的高利貸
was collecting interest at illegal rates.
收取的利息高於合法利率
Using tricks so you'd never pay it off.
用那些技倆，讓你們永遠無法還清
So legally,
所以在法律上
they can't ask for more money than you borrowed.
除了你們借的錢，他們不能要更多
So your sister had already paid more than she owed.
比起欠的，你姐姐已經還了更多
She didn't need to pay any more.
她不用再還錢了
That means…
那意思是…
You have no reason to work.
你沒有打工的理由了
Sir… Thank you so much.
老師…真的非常感謝
Really… Truly…
真的…
Thank you so much.
非常謝謝你
Your ramen is good.
你的拉麵很好吃
Ah, my noodles are soggy now thanks to you.
啊，你害我的拉麵都泡軟了
This one's on you.
這碗你請客
Pardon me.
我先走了
Oh, right.
哦，對了
This is the extra money.
這是多出來的錢
I got it back.
我把它要回來了
Seto.
瀨戶
Depend on people more.
多依靠其他人啊
Huh?
咦？
I can give it back tomorrow.
我明天再還吧
Stand.
起立
Bow.
敬禮
Sit.
坐
Let's get started.
開始吧
Yes, sir.
是
What's this? A newcomer?
這是誰？新學生嗎？
I ironed it for you.
我幫你燙好了
IDIOT
（笨蛋）
I'm Akira Seto.
我是瀨戶輝
I'm joining the UTokyo Special Course today.
今天加入東大專科
Nice to meet you!
請多多指教！
Mizuno.
水野
Yes, sir.
是
Okay, let's begin.
好，開始吧
Ready,
準備
start!
開始！
Everything turned out well!
全部都很順利結束了呢
Not everything. We still only have four students.
還早呢，我們還是只有四位學生
We need one more for our goal.
離目標還差一位
Oh right…
對耶
If we can't get five students into UTokyo,
要是不能把五位學生送進東大
we won't be able to pay this.
我們就無法付這個了
It was for a student.
這是給一位學生的
INVOICE KAORI KISHIMOTO LAW OFFICE
（發票，岸本香法律事務所）
Yes, but…
話是這樣說，但…
Sakuragi!
櫻木！
Thank you very much.
真是非常感謝
What are you saying? I just helped with some research.
這哪有什麼？我只是幫忙做了點調查
Thank you so much.
真的謝謝妳
He seems well, Mr. Sakuragi. He's back!
櫻木老師看來狀態很好 他完全復活了
He's a little too enthusiastic, even for me.
該說他有點熱心過頭了
Do your best to back him up.
儘量支持他吧
I will. Let me complain to you some time.
我會的，就讓我偶爾對妳抱怨一下吧
Sure.
沒問題
Pardon me. You have a visitor.
不好意思，您有一位客人
I have a visitor. I'll call again.
有客人來了，我會再聯繫妳
Okay, goodbye.
好，再見
Long time no see.
好久不見
Yes.
是
It's been a long time.
過了好久了
Mari, Mari! A butterfly!
麻里！蝴蝶！
Mari, a butterfly.
麻里，蝴蝶
-Hello. -Hi.
-你好 -嗨
Let's go, Kenta.
走吧，健太
Another contest?
另一場比賽？
It would be hard for you to win as you are now.
現在的你們很難贏得了藤井
The Special Course would really be eliminated!
這樣下去，專科真的會解散！
Our secret weapon.
我們的秘密武器
-You've got to pass. -I'll try.
-你一定要通過 -我會加油
That one person still hasn't changed.
那人還是沒變
What's 145 times three?
145乘3是多少？
Spartan training in these modern times? Gives me the creeps.
現在這年代還用斯巴達訓練法？ 真是讓我起雞皮疙瘩
You're torturing him with forced study!
你們逼他學習，你們在折磨他！
I don't know what he's thinking.
我真不知道他在想什麼
When they're ready, students will bloom.
當他們準備好時，這些學生都會綻放
Change society.
改變社會
Break the mold.
打破框架
You have to make that world.
就由你來創造出那樣的世界吧
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻譯：楊易